<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>coq on deliberate software</title>
    <link>https://deliberate-software.com/categories/coq/</link>
    <description>Recent content in coq on deliberate software</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 27 Apr 2017 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="https://deliberate-software.com/categories/coq/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Darkest Proof: Day 3</title>
      <link>https://deliberate-software.com/coq_day3/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 27 Apr 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://deliberate-software.com/coq_day3/</guid>
      <description>Day three working through Software Foundations with Coq. Since I like to rant, and I love Darkest Dungeon, ENTER THE DARKEST PROOF. (Please don&amp;rsquo;t sue me!)

I am trying to prove a helper proof to use to rewrite another helper proof to use to rewrite another proof for the commutativity of multiplication. You can&amp;rsquo;t make this stuff up.
I just need to prove this where S n is n + 1:</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Darkest Proof: Day 2</title>
      <link>https://deliberate-software.com/coq-day2/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 07 Feb 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://deliberate-software.com/coq-day2/</guid>
      <description>Day two working through Software Foundations with Coq. Since I like to rant, and I love Darkest Dungeon, ENTER THE DARKEST PROOF. (Please don&amp;rsquo;t sue me!)

Naming While trying to understand how rewrite works, I come across an obvious use-case:
Theorem adding_n_Sm : forall n m : nat, n + S m = S n + m. Proof. intros n. induction n. simpl. reflexivity. simpl. rewrite &amp;lt;- IHn.  At this point, in current scope I have:</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Darkest Proof: Day 1</title>
      <link>https://deliberate-software.com/coq-frustrations/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Feb 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://deliberate-software.com/coq-frustrations/</guid>
      <description>Day one working through Software Foundations with Coq. Since I like to rant, and I love Darkest Dungeon, ENTER THE DARKEST PROOF. (Please don&amp;rsquo;t sue me!)

Precise Syntax I copied a sample from the book by hand, but it always caused Company-Coq to go into an infinite loop. I copied it again. Same deal.
This isn&amp;rsquo;t my first rodeo, I&amp;rsquo;ve seen all sorts of syntax rules and such. But alas, it still fails.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>