<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: clojure | Deliberate Software]]></title>
  <link href="http://deliberate-software.com/blog/categories/clojure/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://deliberate-software.com/"/>
  <updated>2016-02-19T17:09:09-05:00</updated>
  <id>http://deliberate-software.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Steve Shogren]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Conj 2015 - Teaching Clojure]]></title>
    <link href="http://deliberate-software.com/teaching-clojure/"/>
    <updated>2015-11-18T11:19:10-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://deliberate-software.com/teaching-clojure</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>My talk at Conj 2015, enjoy!
<a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=BsLiPt90HDo">Teaching Clojure</a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Language Safety Score Mark 2]]></title>
    <link href="http://deliberate-software.com/safety-rank-part-2/"/>
    <updated>2015-07-24T10:13:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://deliberate-software.com/safety-rank-part-2</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I want to make a model that predicts bugs.</p>

<p>I previously wrote a table for scoring language safety:
<a href="http://deliberate-software.com/programming-language-safety-algorithm/">Programming Language Safety Score</a>,
but it was extremely time consuming to score new languages or make modifications.</p>

<h2>Simplify, Simplify</h2>

<p>After being told I was <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Overfitting">overfitting</a>
the data, I&rsquo;ve attempted to clean up by simply checking if each category is
enforced, possible, or impossible. I score each as either 1 (language enforced),
0 (possible, but you have to remember to do it), or -1 (impossible). When the
magnitudes of the new model are compared with the previous model, they come out
very similar. The shape of the curve pretty much stays the same, which I was
told indicates that the character count weighting was a variable that didn&rsquo;t
matter.</p>

<p><img class="center" src="/images/rplot.jpg" title="&lsquo;image&rsquo; &lsquo;images&rsquo;" ></p>

<p>The code I used to generate the plot and normalize the scores can be found here:
<a href="https://github.com/steveshogren/datasciencecoursera/blob/817dec79e36b6e9a6c5a8fd5700aff7cc394b9d4/scoreplot.R">scorePlot.R</a></p>

<h2>Safety Definitions</h2>

<p>A definition of the safety checks is as follows:</p>

<p><div ng-app="TableApp2">
<div ng-controller="TableCtrl">
<table class="langtable">
<tr><th>Check</th> <th>Description</th></tr>
<tr ng-repeat="check in langChecks">
<td> {{ check.name }} </td>
<td>  {{ check.desc }}  </td>
</tr>
</table></p>

<p>The new scores are shown here, with a lot more languages added in:</p>

<p><p class="lead">
<div style="overflow-x:scroll">
<table class="langtable">
<tr>
<th>Safety Check</th>
<th></th>
<th>
<select ng-options="getName(lang) for lang in allLanguages" ng-model="languages[0]"></select>
</th>
<th>
<select ng-options="getName(lang) for lang in allLanguages" ng-model="languages[1]"></select>
</th>
<th>
<select ng-options="getName(lang) for lang in allLanguages" ng-model="languages[2]"></select>
</th>
<th>
<select ng-options="getName(lang) for lang in allLanguages" ng-model="languages[3]"></select>
</th>
</tr>
<tr ng-repeat="check in langChecks" score-row name="check.name" row-key="check.key"></tr>
<tr class="totals"><td>Totals</td>
<td></td>
<td ng-repeat="lang in langTotals track by $index">
 {{ lang }} 
</td>
</tr>
<tr class="totals"><td>Magnitude</td>
<td></td>
<td ng-repeat="lang in langTotals track by $index">
 {{ percentageTotals(lang) }}% 
</td>
</tr>
</table>
</div></p>

<p>Current Languages:
<span ng-repeat="lang in allLanguages">
 {{ getName(lang) }}: {{ allLangTotals[$index] }}, 
</select></p>

<h2>So, What&rsquo;s the Point?</h2>

<p>To see how this model corresponds with data in the real world, I used the GitHub
API to query for the number of bugs created in repositories with more than 15
forks created in a span from 2011 to 2015. Commits were counted by summing the
commit counts of all contributors.</p>

<p>I decided to rely on the count of commits as a standard for a unit of work. My
assumption was that across fifty different projects, the commit sizes would
average out. Once the unit of work was decided on, I wanted to find the ratio of
bugs per commit for each language.</p>

<p>I collected the ratio of bugs logged per commit for each repository, and after
grouping by primary language, removed the top and bottom 25% using the
bug/commit ratio, which is a common practice in statistics to help find a more
accurate average. I summed the bugs and commits of those remaining repositories
grouped by language, finding a total average bug/commit ratio for each language
grouping. Here is that data, sorted by safety score.</p>

<p><table class="langtable">
<tr><th>Language</th>
<th>Bugs</th>
<th>Commits</th>
<th>Repositories</th>
<th>Bug/Commits</th>
<tr ng-repeat="lang in languageRatios">
<td> {{ lang.name }} </td>
<td> {{ lang.bugs }} </td>
<td> {{ lang.commits }} </td>
<td> {{ lang.repos }} </td>
<td> {{ getBugsRatio(lang) }} </td>
</tr>
</table></p>

<p>Here are the languages sorted by safety score with bug/commit ratios:</p>

<p><img class="center" src="/images/errorChart.jpg" title="&lsquo;image&rsquo; &lsquo;images&rsquo;" >
<img class="center" src="/images/bugsAverage.jpg" title="&lsquo;image&rsquo; &lsquo;images&rsquo;" ></p>

<p>I took the magnitude of the safety scores and the bug/commit ratios. After
inverting the safety scores, I overlaid them both onto a single graph.</p>

<p><img class="center" src="/images/bothMags.jpg" title="&lsquo;image&rsquo; &lsquo;images&rsquo;" ></p>

<p>Immediately it is obvious that Ruby, Python, PHP, and Clojure all seem to strongly
buck the trend, but otherwise the languages follow a pretty consistent slope
down in bugs. Taking the correlation gives a
<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pearson_product-moment_correlation_coefficient">correlation coefficient</a>
of .55</p>

<h2>What About Unit Tests?</h2>

<p>Thinking that Ruby, Clojure, PHP, and Python might not correlate well due to some
other factor, I collected data on how many tests each repository had. I counted
the number of files containing &ldquo;test&rdquo; or &ldquo;spec&rdquo;, which gave the following,
sorted by tests per commit:</p>

<p><table class="langtable">
<tr><th>Language</th>
<th>Tests</th>
<th>Commits</th>
<th>Repositories</th>
<th>Tests/Commits</th></tr>
<tr ng-repeat="lang in sorter(languageRatios)">
<td> {{ lang.name }} </td>
<td> {{ lang.test }} </td>
<td> {{ lang.commits }} </td>
<td> {{ lang.repos }} </td>
<td> {{ getTestsRatio(lang) }} </td>
</tr>
</table></p>

<p>PHP, Python, and Ruby all have a higher then average number of tests, but
Clojure does not. Additionally, Go, Scala, and Java all also have a higher than
average number of tests, yet they score relatively average in bugs/commit.</p>

<h2>Conclusion</h2>

<p>In conclusion, the current safety model I have proposed seems to account for a
moderate reduction in bugs per commit across the sampled languages, but is not
the only factor. It currently is unable to account for a significantly lower
than expected bug count in Ruby and Clojure.</p>

<h2>Special Thanks</h2>

<p>Special thanks to (in alphabetical order):
<a href="https://twitter.com/traffichazard/">Patrick Boe</a> (Haskell, Sniff Test),
<a href="http://asymmetrical-view.com/">Kyle Burton</a> (General Advice),
Nils Creque (Listening Board),
Max Haley (Python, Ruby, Teaching me how to math),
<a href="https://github.com/danielmiladinov">Daniel Miladinov</a> (Java, Scala, Morale Support),
Keith O'Brien (Ruby and JS),
<a href="https://github.com/arlaneenalra">Chris Salch</a> (CoffeeScript and JS),
and <a href="https://github.com/timvisher">Tim Visher</a> (Clojure).</p>

<p>Additional thanks to the posters on
<a href="https://www.reddit.com/r/rust/comments/3egx49/language_safety_score_mark_2/">/r/rust</a>,
including <a href="https://www.reddit.com/user/notriddle">/u/notriddle</a>,
<a href="https://www.reddit.com/user/killercup">/u/killercup</a>, and
<a href="https://www.reddit.com/user/diegobernardes">/u/diegobernardes</a> who put together the Rust score.</p>

<h2>Complaints Department</h2>

<p>Did I mess up something about a language here, or am I missing a safety check? I&rsquo;ll happily take pull
requests for new languages:
<a href="https://github.com/steveshogren/blog-source/blob/master/source/javascripts/sliders2.js">blog source</a>. Just
pick an existing language, edit the name and values, and &ldquo;copy to clipboard&rdquo; to
build your own language data structure. Send it to me in a PR and I&rsquo;ll include
it along with a thanks on the page.</p>

<p><div ng-show="showRealName">
<h2>Select Language:
<select ng-options="lang.name for lang in allLanguages" ng-model="selectedLang"></select>
<button ng-click="copyToClipboard(selectedLang)">Copy Changes to Clipboard</button>
</h2>
<h2><input ng-model="selectedLang.name"></input></h2>
<table class="langtable">
<tr><th>Check</th><th>Option</th></tr>
<tr ng-repeat="check in langChecks">
<td style="background-color: {{scoreClass(score(selectedLang[check.key]))}} ">
 {{ check.name }}:  {{score(selectedLang[check.key]) }} 
</td>
<td>
<select ng-options="enforcedNice(e) for e in enforcedTypes" ng-model="selectedLang[check.key].enforced"></select>
</td>
</tr>
</table></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Learning Lisp Was Hard]]></title>
    <link href="http://deliberate-software.com/learning-lisp-was-hard/"/>
    <updated>2015-06-17T07:02:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://deliberate-software.com/learning-lisp-was-hard</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Several times in the last week people have lamented to me that they &ldquo;just don&rsquo;t
get Lisp&rdquo;. After hearing it for the third time, I thought back to my experience
learning a Lisp.</p>

<p>When I set out to learn a Lisp, I expected it would be easy.</p>

<p>I figured, &ldquo;I am pretty awesome at PHP, and have worked professionally in Perl,
Python, and Java, this should be a cakewalk!&rdquo;. I&rsquo;d read Paul Graham&rsquo;s essays on
how Lisp is his secret weapon, and figured I needed to get into this secret
weapon stuff. My ego said, &ldquo;since Paul is amazing, and I am too, I&rsquo;ll be a
natural!&rdquo;</p>

<p>I expected to tinker around with &ldquo;Lisp&rdquo; (I didn&rsquo;t know there was more
than one) and shortly master it to be able to ship a website with it.</p>

<p>What happened instead took me a little longer&hellip;</p>

<ul>
<li>05/11 - 06/11 - ~15 Hrs Attempted <em>Land Of Lisp</em> (gave up)</li>
<li>04/12 - 08/12 - ~60 Hrs Rewrote a PHP side project in Clojure</li>
<li>08/12 - 08/12 - ~5 Hrs Attempted <em>Let Over Lambda</em> (gave up)</li>
<li>08/12 - 09/12 - ~10 Hrs Read <em>Clojure Programming</em> twice</li>
<li>09/12 - 12/12 - ~30 Hrs Took <em>CS173 Programming Languages</em> online at Brown University</li>
<li>05/13 - 07/13 - ~50 Hrs Worked through <em>Let Over Lambda</em></li>
<li>05/13 - 07/14 - ~250 Hrs Worked through <em>SICP</em></li>
<li>07/14 - Shipped production Clojure code</li>
</ul>


<p>This shows only the major events: books and large projects, but doesn&rsquo;t show all
the countless blogs, tutorials, and tiny projects that also filled in the gaps.</p>

<p>I think Lisps started to &ldquo;click&rdquo; for me around mid 2013, about two years after
deciding that I&rsquo;d &ldquo;tinker around&rdquo; for a bit before &ldquo;mastering&rdquo; it. I was
approximately 170 hours in at that point. The book that finally made it all
click was <em>Let Over Lambda</em>, but it took me two attempts and almost a year of
pre-learning to be able to understand enough to internalize the material.</p>

<p>All said and done, I spent approximately 420 hours between Common Lisp, Racket,
Typed Racket, and Clojure before I felt confident enough to suggest shipping
Clojure at work. I don&rsquo;t claim to be a fast learner at all, and I fully expect
some people will snort with derision at how much time it took me - which is kind
of the point of this post.</p>

<p>This timeline should show those who are struggling that what you are feeling is
normal. Learning anything new is hard. The more &ldquo;new&rdquo; it is, the harder it will
be. Clojure, macros, emacs, and a repl workflow are all very different from
everything I was used to and significantly more powerful than I would&rsquo;ve
guessed. It took a long time for that to become normal, and for that power to
sink in and become a tool I anticipated having.</p>

<p>If you are struggling and feel like a failure, understand <em>there is no wrong
way</em>. It might take you a long time of repeated exposure before the alien
tooling starts to look familiar, and then comfortable. Maybe that book you are
struggling with actually IS too advanced, so find an easier one, and circle back
to the harder book later. Maybe, like me, you need some part of many different
books, tutorials, side projects, and katas.</p>

<p>If you are struggling learning and in the Philly area, I am happy to meet up to
chat. I am also happy to help over the wire as well. I understand how
demoralizing the constant battle is to learn something new, especially when it
feels like your ego is on the line and the whole internet is pressuring you to
learn new things. Don&rsquo;t give up, it&rsquo;s not impossible.</p>

<h1>Was it worth it?</h1>

<p>I can anticipate the follow up question: &ldquo;was it worth it?&rdquo; Absolutely yes. I
now feel a fluid comfort with my current professional stack (C#, F#, Clojure,
and JS) that previously I did not have. I am significantly more productive at
programming, regardless of the language. Work that was previously challenging is
now trivial, and work that was previously &ldquo;impossible&rdquo; now feels fun and
challenging. Was it learning Lisp specifically that caused all those changes?
Probably not, but I believe it was learning something far outside my normal
comfort zone that made the difference. I think I would have had equivalent
experiences had I invested that time learning Scala (the ML parts), Haskell,
Idris, J, R, Forth, etc.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Programming Language Safety Score]]></title>
    <link href="http://deliberate-software.com/programming-language-safety-algorithm/"/>
    <updated>2015-02-17T14:13:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://deliberate-software.com/programming-language-safety-algorithm</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I think the time has come for a standard programming language safety
score. I want to use this model to help show that the concept of
safety is much more nuanced than a binary bit of &ldquo;has strong-static
types&rdquo;.</p>

<p>When someone says &ldquo;programming language safety&rdquo;, it typically invokes
thoughts of unit tests, long build times, and red squiggles in an
IDE. But, in day-to-day development, there are so many times when we
are bitten by things that somehow just slip through the cracks.</p>

<p>I put together this scoring model to get a sense of how safe a
language is at the primitive level, and if it isn&rsquo;t safe by default,
how much it costs to manually make it safe. Since all abstractions
eventually result in a series of primitive operations, I decided that
focusing only on primitives would still be a valuable (if incomplete)
data point. While any good library will handle all primitive checks
and present the consumer with a well-designed abstraction, in the end,
the consumer is still left wiring libraries together, building their
own primitive abstractions for integration. Due to the impossibility of
measuring the quality of abstractions in all libraries for a language,
I left that entirely out of scope of this model, unless it is designed
as a primitive check.</p>

<p>By focusing on only primitive operations: making and calling
functions, naming data, working with sequences, and dealing with
language primitive data types, I slimmed down the large range of
possible error vectors to a small handful. While in some languages it
is common to use user-defined classes to wrap around a set of
primitives, those classes are still doing the same primitive work,
just hidden behind a user-created abstraction. The more ways it is
possible to make a &ldquo;mistake&rdquo; with a primitive, the more difficult it
is to build such good abstractions.</p>

<pre><code>This model is not about language "power".
</code></pre>

<p>This model is not about ranking the &ldquo;power&rdquo;, &ldquo;expressiveness&rdquo;, or
&ldquo;abstract-ability&rdquo; of a language. In any language that supports
abstractions (functions, classes, modules, naming data), I am
convinced, given enough code, all Turing complete langauges can do the
same work. This model is only about the costs to prevent unexpected
&ldquo;confusion&rdquo; between the programmer and the machine at the primitive
level.</p>

<p>Rather than focus on what is <em>possible</em> with a language, I will
instead focus on what is typically idiomatic to that community. For
example, if it is possible to achieve a level of safety in a language
but by doing something uncommon, that should not be counted.</p>

<p>To score a language, simply figure out how many characters it costs to
&ldquo;prevent&rdquo; a certain type of error, and add that to the
total. Newlines, spaces, and tabs do not count, but all other
punctuation does. If a specific check is language enforced, like F#&rsquo;s
Option or C#&rsquo;s parameter type enforcement, that is given a -30 (by
default) to make up for the lack of unit tests and code exercising
needed to run that &ldquo;path&rdquo;. Do not count import lines for libraries, as
importing the module will have a negligible effect on the code size
and complexity.</p>

<p>If there is a safety feature that is not possible to achieve
programmatically, we will add +30 (by default) for a &ldquo;every change run
and debug to fix&rdquo; cost, such as Java not having a way to prevent stack
overflow exceptions caused by recursion.</p>

<pre><code>A lower score is "safer", needing less (or no) code to achieve the same level of safety.
</code></pre>

<p>Rather than tell you my thoughts (or survey for) hard-coded
weightings, all checks are weighted the same by default. Feel free to
apply your own weightings, to better match to your or your team&rsquo;s
specific needs and preferences. The languages are masked by default to
protect the innocent. You can unmask the names and see the code used
below the table.</p>

<p><div ng-app="TableApp">
<div ng-controller="TableCtrl"></p>

<p>Language Enforced Bonus:
 {{ enforcedScore }} 
<input ng-model="enforcedScore" type="range" min="0" max="50" /></p>

<p>Language Inability Penalty:
 {{ inabilityPenalty }} 
<input ng-model="inabilityPenalty" type="range" min="0" max="50" /></p>

<p>Show Weights <input type="checkbox" ng-model="showWeights" />
<p class="lead">
<div style="overflow-x:scroll">
<table class="langtable">
<tr>
<th>Safety Check</th>
<th></th>
<th>
<select ng-options="getName(lang) for lang in allLanguages" ng-model="languages[0]"></select>
</th>
<th>
<select ng-options="getName(lang) for lang in allLanguages" ng-model="languages[1]"></select>
</th>
<th>
<select ng-options="getName(lang) for lang in allLanguages" ng-model="languages[2]"></select>
</th>
<th>
<select ng-options="getName(lang) for lang in allLanguages" ng-model="languages[3]"></select>
</th>
</tr>
<tr ng-repeat="check in langChecks" score-row name="check.name" row-key="check.key"></tr>
<tr class="totals"><td>Totals</td>
<td></td>
<td ng-repeat="lang in langTotals track by $index">
 {{ lang }} 
</td>
</tr>
<tr class="totals"><td>Magnitude</td>
<td></td>
<td ng-repeat="lang in langTotals track by $index">
 {{ percentageTotals(lang) }}% 
</td>
</tr>
</table>
</div></p>

<p><h3><input ng-model="showRealName" type="checkbox" /><span
ng-click="showRealName = !!!showRealName">Click to see backing code and unmask names</span></h3></p>

<p>Current Languages:
<span ng-repeat="lang in allLanguages">
 {{ getName(lang) }}: {{ allLangTotals[$index] }}, 
</select></p>

<p>I want to see your language represented here! I&rsquo;ll happily take pull
requests for new languages: <a href="https://github.com/steveshogren/blog-source/blob/master/source/javascripts/sliders.js">blog source</a>. Just
use the &ldquo;edit language&rdquo; and &ldquo;copy to clipboard&rdquo; to build your own
language data structure.</p>

<p>I would love to see every major language represented, including major
language &ldquo;idiom communities&rdquo;. For example, Clojure and Typed Clojure
are vastly different in abilities. Similarly &ldquo;Scala - The Better Java&rdquo;
and &ldquo;Scala - The JVM Haskell&rdquo; have vastly different idioms with
apparently very separate communities.</p>

<p><div ng-show="showRealName"> Feel free to put in your own examples by
playing with the samples below. Code surrounded with &lt;! !> is ignored
from the tally, since it would vary heavily based on the language and
desired result. Variable and type names are kept at single characters,
which are counted. Feel free to add in your own language below, and
use the copy feature to extract the data structure to use in a pull
request.</p>

<p><h2>Select Language:
<select ng-options="lang.name for lang in allLanguages" ng-model="selectedLang"></select>
</h2>
<button ng-click="showEdit = !showEdit">Edit Language</button>
<button ng-click="copyToClipboard(selectedLang)">Copy Changes to Clipboard</button>
<div ng-show="showEdit">
<h2><input ng-model="selectedLang.name"></input></h2>
<div ng-repeat="check in langChecks">
<h3> {{ check.name }} :  {{ score(selectedLang[check.key]) }}  </h3>
<p>
<textarea class="widetextarea" rows="5" ng-model="selectedLang[check.key].desc"></textarea>
<div>
Code: <select ng-options="enforcedNice(e) for e in enforcedTypes" ng-model="selectedLang[check.key].enforced"></select>
<div class="tablecode">1234567890123456789012345678901234567890</div>
<div class="tablecode" >  {{ cleanCode(selectedLang[check.key].rawCode) }}  </div>
<input type="text" style="width:90%;" ng-model="selectedLang[check.key].rawCode" />
</div>
</p>
</div>
</div></p>

<p><div ng-show="!showEdit">
<h2> {{ selectedLang.name }} </h2>
<div ng-repeat="check in langChecks">
<h3> {{ check.name }} :  {{ score(selectedLang[check.key]) }}  </h3>
<p>
 {{ selectedLang[check.key].desc }} 
<div>
Code:  {{ enforcedNice(selectedLang[check.key].enforced)  }} 
<div class="tablecode" ng-if="selectedLang[check.key].rawCode">1234567890123456789012345678901234567890</div>
<div class="tablecode" >  {{ cleanCode(selectedLang[check.key].rawCode) }}  </div>
<input type="text" style="width:90%;" ng-model="selectedLang[check.key].rawCode" />
</div>
</p>
</div>
</div>
</div></p>

<p>Hope this is a helpful way to think about language safety!</p>

<p>Special thanks to (in alphabetical order):
Patrick Boe <a href="https://twitter.com/traffichazard/">(twitter)</a>,
Kyle Burton <a href="http://asymmetrical-view.com/">(blog)</a>,
Daniel Miladinov <a href="https://github.com/danielmiladinov">(github)</a>,
Chris Salch <a href="https://github.com/arlaneenalra">(github)</a>, and
Tim Visher <a href="https://github.com/timvisher">(github)</a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Six Unusual Reasons Why Clojure Is a Delight]]></title>
    <link href="http://deliberate-software.com/unusual-reasons-why-clojure-is-a-delight/"/>
    <updated>2015-02-09T11:36:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://deliberate-software.com/unusual-reasons-why-clojure-is-a-delight</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Clojure is a delightful language, and here are six uncommonly
discussed reasons why.</p>

<h2>1 - Dead Simple Unit Test Mocking</h2>

<p>Clojure is the easiest language to unit test I have ever
seen. &ldquo;Mocking&rdquo; a function in a test only requires a simple
replacement of the function definition. No extraneous interfaces, no
dependency injection, no mocking framework.  The built-in function <code>with-redefs</code>
will replace any function in any library or
namespace with a new definition.</p>

<pre><code class="clojure">(defn next-id [connection]
  (+ 1 (get-current-id connection)))

(testing "next-id"
  ;; bind get-current-id to a lambda that always returns 4 
  (with-redefs [get-current-id (fn [_] 4)]
    (is (= 5 (next-id nil)))))
</code></pre>

<p>We &ldquo;mock&rdquo; the <code>get-current-id</code> function to always return 4 inside
the scope of <code>with-redefs</code>. Couldn&rsquo;t be more simple! The binding
only is in scope for code inside and called by the s-expression of the
with-redefs, so no need to unbind it after the test.</p>

<h2>2 - Amazing Editing</h2>

<p>Many arguments have been made over those contentious
parentheses. While the most powerful use of s-expressions is to easily
allow macros, for the day to day, s-expressions have a very important
use: amazing editing!</p>

<p><img class="center <a" src="href="http://danmidwood.com/assets/animated-paredit/paredit-slurp-barf.gif">http://danmidwood.com/assets/animated-paredit/paredit-slurp-barf.gif</a>" title="&lsquo;image&rsquo; &lsquo;images&rsquo;" ></p>

<p>With ParEdit (available in most editors), it is trivial to select,
move, replace, grow, or shrink any s-expression, string, map, or
list. <a href="http://danmidwood.com/content/2014/11/21/animated-paredit.html">This animated guide</a>
shows excellent examples of ParEdit that are too
complex to explain here.</p>

<p>Languages that don&rsquo;t have a surrounding delimiter for expressions
leave you jumping around with the mouse and arrow keys a whole lot more.
Because it is so much easier to write a parser to select <code>(add 1 2)</code>
than it is for <code>add(1, 2)</code>, the tooling can be so much better.</p>

<p>No local editing tool I have seen comes close to Vim with ParEdit for
effective editing.</p>

<h2>3 - Live Attached Repl</h2>

<p>Developing in Clojure against a running version of the program is a
huge bonus for development speed. While possible to get similar
behavior with an attached debugger in other languages, the fluidity of
an always-on live attached repl is incredible. At any point, it is
possible to run and rerun any given expression to see the
results. More than once, I have seen an exception caused by calling a
certain function. I trace that function to see the exact inputs that
cause the exception, and am able to quickly run every line of the
offending function to see the source.</p>

<p>If a debugger sheds light on a single line at a time when running an
application, a live attached repl sheds light on the entire
application.</p>

<h2>4 - No-fuss Polymorphism</h2>

<p>One of the best claims about &ldquo;traditional&rdquo; Java OO is
polymorphism. The ability to make an interface with concrete classes
gives the powerful ability to replace behavior dynamically. The
trouble is, Java&rsquo;s polymorphic dynamic dispatch is single dispatch - the
decision of which method to call is limited to a single thing: the
type of the callee. If this was the only type of dynamic dispatch you
ever knew of, it might be hard for you to consciously realize it was
ever a limitation, especially if you&rsquo;ve never seen examples of
multiple dispatch.</p>

<p>While most of the time, in any language with first class functions, it
is possible to achieve a similar effect by passing functions, it is
also possible to get a similar value with something called multimethods.</p>

<pre><code class="clojure">(defmulti speak :animal)
(defmethod speak :dog [this] (str "woof says " (:name this)))
(defmethod speak :cat [this] (str "mow says " (:name this)))

(speak {:animal :dog :id 1 :name "Spike"})
;; =&gt; "woof says Spike"
(speak {:animal :cat :id 2 :name "Mr Cat"})
;; =&gt; "mow says Mr Cat"
</code></pre>

<p>In this example, we use the <code>:animal</code> keyword to be the &ldquo;route&rdquo; function,
and the two methods fill in two of the possible concrete types. We are
not limited to just a keyword, we can dispatch on anything on the
passed map, for example, the oddness of the id:</p>

<pre><code class="clojure">(defmulti odds? (comp odd? :id))
(defmethod odds? true [d] "odd id")
(defmethod odds? false [c] "even id")

(odds? {:animal :dog :id 1 :name "Spike"})
;; =&gt; "odd id"
(odds? {:animal :cat :id 2 :name "Mr Cat"})
;; =&gt; "even id"
</code></pre>

<p>While both examples are a bit silly, they should demonstrate the power
of simple polymorphism. But you might think, what about inheritance?
Multimethods allow that too!</p>

<h2>5 - Simple Multiple Inheritance</h2>

<p>We don&rsquo;t build inheritance on a single type, but on a hierarchy of
keywords. Those can be dispatched on just like any other
keyword. First, an example hierarchy of keywords using the built-in
functions <code>derive</code> and <code>isa?</code>. These <code>::</code> keywords are
namespaced, which prevents collisions.</p>

<pre><code class="clojure">(derive ::cat ::mammal)
(derive ::dog ::mammal)
(derive ::dog ::hairy)
(derive ::poodle ::dog)

(isa? ::poodle ::dog)
;; =&gt; true
(isa? ::poodle ::mammal)
;; =&gt; true
(isa? ::poodle ::hairy)
;; =&gt; true
(isa? ::poodle ::cat)
;; =&gt; false
(isa? ::mammal ::hairy)
;; =&gt; false
</code></pre>

<p>A <code>::dog</code> is-a <code>::mammal</code> and is-a <code>::hairy</code>, the
classical diamond problem (without the common ancestor, which is
possible, but unneeded for the example).</p>

<pre><code class="clojure">(defmulti speak :animal)
(defmethod speak ::poodle [d] "chirps")
(defmethod speak ::mammal [c] "breathes")

(speak {:animal ::poodle :id 1 :name "Spike"})
;; =&gt; "chirps"
(speak {:animal ::dog :id 2 :name "Mr Dog"})
;; =&gt; "breathes"

(defmulti shave :animal)
(defmethod shave ::poodle [d] "shivers")
(defmethod shave ::hairy [c] "stuggles")
(defmethod shave ::mammal [c] "maybe cant be shaved!")
(prefer-method shave ::hairy ::mammal)

(shave {:animal ::poodle :id 1 :name "Spike"})
;; =&gt; "shivers"
(shave {:animal ::dog :id 2 :name "Rufs"})
;; =&gt; "stuggles"
</code></pre>

<p>We can see the <code>::dog</code> keyword doesn&rsquo;t have an explicit speak or shave
implementation, which is fine, because it will then use the &ldquo;preferred&rdquo;
parent implementation, which returns &ldquo;breathes&rdquo; for speak or
&ldquo;struggles&rdquo; for shave. Since we can have a keyword be the child of
multiple parents, we get a multiple inherited behavior, where the
preferred match is the one returned.</p>

<p>This is possible because the default equality check of multimethod is
the <code>isa?</code> function. Because of this, uses of multimethod
hierarchies can have inherited behavior for complex structures.</p>

<h2>6 - Mostly Monadic</h2>

<p>Languages like Haskell and F# have tools like the maybe monad that add
safety to operations. For example, using the maybe monad can
completely prevent null reference exceptions by making you ensure you
&ldquo;unpack&rdquo; the value every time.</p>

<p>How does Clojure address this? In a typical Clojure way, which gives
80% of the value for 20% of the effort, Clojure has a great
relationship with empty lists and nil. Rather than wrapping every
value that is nullable in a type, Clojure&rsquo;s default functions all
<em>mostly</em> deal with nil and empty without throwing exceptions. For
example:</p>

<pre><code class="clojure">(get {:id 5} :id)
;; =&gt; 5
(get nil :id)
;; =&gt; nil

(first [3 2 1])
;; =&gt; 3
(first nil)
;; =&gt; nil
(count nil)
;; =&gt; 0
</code></pre>

<p>This allows functions to be chained without fear that along the way a
nil will get returned.</p>

<p>Since most of the core functions are &ldquo;smart&rdquo; about nil, you gain much
of the value and safety of monads without most of the
hassle. Ultimately, a more rich type system would allow for custom
types which can be domain specific, but in day-to-day working,
primitive safety is still a huge win.</p>

<h2>Conclusion</h2>

<p>These are a few simple features that keep me coming back to Clojure,
even from languages like F# and Haskell. While Clojure is a bit more
wordy than the ML family, and not as type safe, the simplicity of
these features keep me coming back for more!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
