<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: management | Deliberate Software]]></title>
  <link href="http://deliberate-software.com/blog/categories/management/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://deliberate-software.com/"/>
  <updated>2016-02-05T07:12:27-05:00</updated>
  <id>http://deliberate-software.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Steve Shogren]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Development Disappointment Disorder]]></title>
    <link href="http://deliberate-software.com/development-disappointment-disorder/"/>
    <updated>2016-02-04T16:58:25-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://deliberate-software.com/development-disappointment-disorder</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<blockquote><p>&ldquo;We&rsquo;ve never had a successful release&rdquo;</p></blockquote>

<p>You just finished this really hard feature. The whole thing was worse than
anyone realized. Not only that, but the feature wasn&rsquo;t clearly explained, so you
lost time churning on the actual requirements. Despite all the confusion,
iteration, and technical challenges, you managed to get it working! You look
back, savoring how much you have learned and grown.</p>

<p>You show it off to the product owner. He barely seems to hear you. His shoulders
slump in disappointment.</p>

<blockquote><p>&ldquo;Great, but we are still four weeks behind.&rdquo;</p></blockquote>

<p>Your team is infected with <strong>Development Disappointment Disorder</strong>.</p>

<p>It looks different in every team. The manager who sets unreasonable deadlines
then demands overtime. The project manager who gets angry at every little thing.
Developers who feel they need to point fingers to shift the blame. The boss who
is never happy no matter what is achieved. The team that feels they have never
had a successful release.</p>

<h2>Unreasonable Expectations</h2>

<p><strong>Development Disappointment Disorder is caused by unreasonable expectations.</strong>
Someone thinks, hopes, or wishes they can get 100 units of productivity from a
team and codebase that only can sustain 30-40 units. They want the impossible,
and no amount of cajoling, pressuring, yelling, or passive aggressive comments
will change reality.</p>

<p>Productivity is not completely a people problem. Every team has an upper limit
to what they can produce in a system. The human mind has boundaries. Very real
limits exist given the team&rsquo;s size and existing codebases. While new technical
tools and libraries enable more productive teams, these changes often are
hindered by an existing codebase. The team with a multi-million line C# codebase
is not going to get much value from the productivity gains possible with
Haskell&rsquo;s type system.</p>

<p>You cannot rush software development without incurring a drop in quality,
stability, or maintainability. The work is complex and difficult: every expert
in our field agrees with adages like &ldquo;adding developers to a late project makes
it later.&rdquo;</p>

<h2>Suggestions</h2>

<ul>
<li><p><strong>For the technical staff:</strong> How accurate are your estimates? How consistent
is your throughput? Do you regularly under-estimate your features? Do
developers often say, &ldquo;oh, that&rsquo;s only&hellip;&rdquo;? Are some types of features &ldquo;always
late&rdquo;?</p>

<p>You must learn to be blameless in this situation, and that means striving to
give as accurate an estimate as you can with what you have. Throwing estimates
out without much thought only makes things worse. How long did a similar
feature take last time? If you regularly have inaccurate estimates in a
certain area of the system, put extra care into those estimates, working to
provide the best estimate you can.</p></li>
<li><p><strong>For the business:</strong> There is only so many units of productivity that fit
into a given time frame.You need to assess every feature and estimate, and
consider the risk with each.</p>

<p>Acting disappointed, angry, or passive aggressive will not get you more
features, it will only demotivate the technical staff. You will get more
consistency, because they will consistently work slower. You will get more
hours, but each hour will see a
<a href="http://www.igda.org/?page=crunchsixlessons">massive drop in valuable work.</a></p></li>
</ul>


<blockquote><p>Acting disappointed, angry, or passive aggressive will not get you more features</p></blockquote>

<p>  If you are unhappy with the work produced, you need to consider why. Were you
  told it would be sooner? Did you promise that to someone? What changed since
  then? If the feature isn&rsquo;t actually needed, why did you pick it? If spending
  twice as much made it not worthwhile, was it really a good choice?</p>

<p>  What would happen if you didn&rsquo;t promise <em>when</em> the features would be done?
  Either way, your promise doesn&rsquo;t change when it will be done, it just adds
  risk to your credibility. Often the only thing to be gained by giving out
  estimates and time-lines is risk. Unless the customer is truly blocked on your
  estimate, simply communicate what you are doing, not when you hope it will be
  done.</p>

<blockquote><p>Often the only thing to be gained by telling customers an estimate is risk</p></blockquote>

<ul>
<li><strong>For the team:</strong> Celebrate your successes. Abolish the notion of a &ldquo;failed
release&rdquo;. Build up a culture that finds little victories throughout the
release.</li>
</ul>


<p>With these tools you can fight Development Disappointment Disorder. You can
start to celebrate what you do accomplish. <strong>A team that is energized and motivated will accomplish more.</strong> The team that celebrates their work will strive for more.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Designing A Compassionate Interview For A High Performing Individual]]></title>
    <link href="http://deliberate-software.com/compassionate-interviewing/"/>
    <updated>2016-01-11T07:01:58-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://deliberate-software.com/compassionate-interviewing</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img class="right emailImage" src="/images/2.Why_Algorithm_Important.png" width="400" title="&lsquo;finding&rsquo; &lsquo;finding&rsquo;" ></p>

<p>After my post <a href="http://deliberate-software.com/on-defeat/">Interview Humiliation</a>, a number of
people have asked me how I interview compassionately. I strive to make my interviews as
stress-free and respectful as possible while still rendering a yes/no at the end.</p>

<p>Any good interview process needs to start with goals:</p>

<ul>
<li>Respect the candidate&rsquo;s time</li>
<li>Make the candidate comfortable</li>
<li>Under-skilled candidates should feel no shame</li>
<li>Both passing and failing candidates should want to tell their friends to
apply</li>
<li>We should render the same decision if the interview is repeated multiple
times (with different exercises each time)</li>
<li>The candidate should know the process in advance and not be able to earn a
pass through short term &ldquo;cramming&rdquo;</li>
<li>The candidate should feel we are all working collaboratively, instead of us
against them</li>
</ul>


<h2>The Ideal Candidate</h2>

<p><img class="right emailImage" src="/images/whiteboards2.jpg" width="400" title="&lsquo;whiteboard 'whiteboard&rsquo;" ></p>

<p>We want to hire for high-level skills. Fast learning, strategic thinking, good
design, and emotional intelligence are more important than rote memorization. We
care more about &ldquo;ability to grow&rdquo; than &ldquo;current skills&rdquo;. Our job does not
involve whiteboard coding, puzzle questions, or anything that can be discovered
with a decent IDE, so those are left out.</p>

<p>We care a lot about &ldquo;no jerks&rdquo;. We want our workplace to be fun, relaxing, and
supportive. We want candidates who are comfortable being wrong and corrected
regularly, and who can correct others politely.</p>

<p>We do not care about any question that could be easily be answered by Google. If
an internet search can easily answer the question, it is pointless to care if
the human in front of me happens to know it. Given the search revolution of the
last decade, the value of memorized facts falls to almost zero. Facts as a proxy
for actual job skill probably used to be accurate until the internet allowed
every interview question to become public record.</p>

<h2>Scoring</h2>

<p>I hope someone one day invents a perfect productivity score! For now, counting
bugs, features, correct answers, etc, are all proxies that poorly represent
actual productivity. If those actually worked, why don&rsquo;t we use them for raises,
bonuses, and reviews? Because. They. Do. Not. Work.</p>

<blockquote><p>Counting bugs, features, correct answers, etc, are all proxies that poorly
represent actual productivity</p></blockquote>

<p>A well-designed rubric <em>can</em> work. A rubric is a way of measuring the
&ldquo;un-measurable&rdquo;. You probably have seen them in year-end reviews. A grid with
categories on one side, and a 1-5 score with a paragraph explanation for each.
We only score what has to be explained with a description from the interviewers.</p>

<blockquote><p>&ldquo;How was the candidate&rsquo;s communication skills?&rdquo;</p>

<p>&ldquo;They misunderstood me only a few times, and I only had trouble understanding
them once or twice. The watchers all felt like the communication was pretty
good. They were definitely above average: &frac34;.&rdquo;</p>

<p>&ldquo;How about design skills?&rdquo;</p>

<p>&ldquo;They were able to clearly design every abstraction. They deeply understood
passing functions as values, see how this takes a function for polymorphism?
We prodded a bit, and they were able to give a couple other ways to achieve
the same behavior. We all agreed it was best the way it was. All said, they
did most of the heavy lifting for this whole project, and it is superbly
designed: 4/4&rdquo;</p></blockquote>

<h2>Our Process</h2>

<p>To &ldquo;level-set&rdquo; our expectations, we had several of our developers at different
levels perform the interview live in front of the team. We made them use various
languages and exercises they had never seen before. This &ldquo;level-setting&rdquo; helped
us to see how known good developers perform when way out of their element and
uncomfortable.</p>

<p>All interviews are assigned to developers randomly, and all are expected to
participate. The candidate should have two developers around at all time, to
prevent bias by any individual. One pairs while the others rotate watching
silently. The watchers are expected to stay quiet, to prevent confusion.</p>

<p>Before the first interview, the candidate is sent something very much like this
document. We think there is no way someone could &ldquo;fake us out&rdquo; on any criteria.
The things we look for take years of practice to cultivate, so &ldquo;cramming&rdquo; should
not help much (if at all). The one exception to that is if they have never heard
of Test Driven Development, we do recommend they Google it for a few minutes, as
prior knowledge helps smooth the phone screen considerably.</p>

<h3>Phone Screen</h3>

<p>We pair program over the internet using a shared programming environment called
<a href="c9.io">Cloud9</a>. We (currently) have projects set up for Java, JavaScript,
Python, Ruby, and C#. The candidate may choose their desired language. We then
pair program using Test Driven Development to build out a well defined exercise.
The candidate may entirely verbally &ldquo;navigate&rdquo;, while one of our programmers
entirely &ldquo;drives&rdquo; and types out the code. This is acceptable.</p>

<p>If the candidate has never seen any of those languages, Google or asking the
interviewer is totally fair game, and does not count against them. If the
candidate has completely no idea, the interviewer is expected to politely
complete the task while keeping the candidate engaged.</p>

<p>The phone screen is under an hour, with 30 minutes for the pair programming.
The remaining time is for questions about our office. We let them drive the
second half of the interview, asking us questions about what our team and
process is like. We attempt to answer clearly and honestly, both good and bad.</p>

<h3>In-Person</h3>

<p>The in-person interview is from 9:30 to 3:00. We are not thrilled with how much
time it takes and would like to shorten it, but so far have no superior
alternatives.</p>

<p>At the start of the day, we spend 30 minutes chatting and asking questions back
and forth. Our questions are meant to tell us about the candidate&rsquo;s background
and &ldquo;programming philosophy&rdquo;: books read, favorite languages, interesting
projects they&rsquo;ve worked on, etc. We allow them as many questions as they would
like.</p>

<p>The rest of the day is very much like a &ldquo;typical day at work&rdquo;, but with
programming exercises instead of production code. We pair program on the
exercises, following the same flow from the phone screen. The exercises have no
&ldquo;tricks&rdquo;, they are reasonably straightforward and don&rsquo;t require any prior domain
or CS theory knowledge. Throughout the day, the candidate is free to get food,
drinks, and run to the restroom.</p>

<p>The developer who is pairing has a primary role of making the candidate feel
comfortable and accomplish any effort with a 50/50 split of effort. If the
candidate really is struggling, the developer is expected to keep working with
the candidate, even to the point of doing the hard parts and giving them the
easy parts. A completely unskilled candidate will see their pair doing all the
work with a smile and politely asking for &ldquo;help&rdquo; with variable names and such.</p>

<p>The developer pair is also expected to give the candidate some time to think
if they are lost. The candidate at the end of the interview should feel like
they have a complete understanding of what happened. The exercises are
designed to be &ldquo;too much to finish&rdquo;, and as such finishing the exercises is
not a success criteria as much as working well together and writing
maintainable code.</p>

<p>We feel this gives us a highly accurate understanding of a candidate&rsquo;s skill,
while still putting them at ease. Many times we&rsquo;ve seen a terrified candidate
light up fifteen minutes into a pairing session while watching their developer
pair do most of the work. Something about seeing code written &ldquo;activates&rdquo; even
the most nervous candidate. All the thoughts of nerves turn into a concrete
&ldquo;oh, wait, I know what he just did, and I&rsquo;ve got an opinion on that!&rdquo;</p>

<h2>Conclusion</h2>

<p>We like this process because it is exactly what our job is like. We pair program
for a lot of work, and the interview is meant to give candidates a sample of
that. No one should show up for their first day of work and say, &ldquo;wait, I
actually hate pair programming.&rdquo; By thinking through our goals and an &ldquo;ideal
candidate&rdquo;, we were able to design a process that meets those goals.</p>

<p>I recommend you take an hour to write out your goals and needs. Then see how
your interview process matches. Are you looking for a &ldquo;human Google&rdquo;? Does your
job involve whiteboard coding? Would telling the candidate the exact process in
advance with all the questions let them game the system? Because every single
interview question I&rsquo;ve seen is up on Google to be found and memorized on easy
to read lists. How much time does your process take? Could it be shortened? Does
it require the candidate to spend a lot of time at home? You might be surprised
at what you find!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[How Daily Meditation Improved My Technical Leadership]]></title>
    <link href="http://deliberate-software.com/daily-meditation-greatly-improved-my-technical-leadership/"/>
    <updated>2015-12-14T07:50:38-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://deliberate-software.com/daily-meditation-greatly-improved-my-technical-leadership</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img class="right emailImage" src="/images/meditation.jpg" width="200" title="&lsquo;meditation&rsquo; &lsquo;meditation&rsquo;" ></p>

<p>A couple years ago, a coworker told me a success story about mindful meditation.
He explained how his wife took a class that required an hour of daily meditation
for a whole month. He reported that she found it uncomfortable, but the effects
were astounding. She claimed to feel more relaxed, more focused, and more
&ldquo;herself&rdquo;. She found new reserves of motivation. She dropped the book she&rsquo;d been
trying to write for years, and started a business. After that business failed,
she started another, this time successfully.</p>

<p>Immediately convinced, I started by listening to guided
<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mindfulness#Mindfulness_meditation">mindfulness meditations</a>
on YouTube and <a href="https://www.headspace.com/science">phone apps</a>. After a couple
weeks of that, I started doing breathing exercises on my own while sitting
listening to rain sounds. I made a habit of doing it for about an hour every day
on my lunch break. A few months later, I hated it.</p>

<p>For whatever reason, after each session I would feel very uncomfortable. I would
be confronted with emotions that made me feel worthless and embarrassed. My mind
was bringing forward all these painful memories and feelings. Over time, I
started to dread the lunch break.</p>

<h2>The Revelation</h2>

<p>Then, one day, I had a profound sense of understanding. I realized what was
causing these negative emotions. I was in the middle of a major push to guide
our team to adopt a new programming language. While I&rsquo;d led many such
initiatives before, I saw that I&rsquo;d always had the same struggles. My ego and
self-worth were so tied into &ldquo;my&rdquo; campaigns that I wasn&rsquo;t able to clearly hear
criticism. When people pointed out legitimate concerns or weaknesses, I would
get embarrassed and take it as a personal failure.</p>

<p>I could see, from the very beginning, my current &ldquo;campaign&rdquo; had been poorly
executed. After researching the new technology for a long time, I felt like I
saw a place where it could solve some of our needs. Instead of carefully writing
out a proposal, I &ldquo;half-jokingly&rdquo; brought it up whenever I could. When the
listeners didn&rsquo;t immediately react positively, I quickly retracted the idea,
&ldquo;just kidding&rdquo;. Over weeks I dropped not-so-subtle hints, &ldquo;this would be better
with&hellip;&rdquo;, or, &ldquo;we wouldn&rsquo;t have this problem if&hellip;&rdquo;. Instead of convincing
anyone of anything, I just broadcasted to everyone how insecure I felt about the
issue. Everyone could clearly see that I cared, but I was too afraid to put
myself out there and make a serious suggestion. For months nothing changed, and
I felt more and more bitter that &ldquo;my idea&rdquo; wasn&rsquo;t being listened to. In reality,
I hadn&rsquo;t even made a serious suggestion yet!</p>

<p>Eventually, the people around me started to listen and research the new
language. They agreed it really did solve a need we had. After a while, enough
people got on board that we started using it more. Even then, I held tightly to
&ldquo;my idea&rdquo;, afraid that it would prove to be a failure. When someone ran into
issues, I would get defensive. Even though I tried to keep my emotions in check,
I clearly took any criticism of the language as if it was a personal failing, no
matter how legitimate. I&rsquo;d tightly coupled my ego to my ideas, and I always had.</p>

<p>After a few months of meditating, this idea rocked my world. My negative
emotions came from a realization that my actions were not in line with my
values. I don&rsquo;t want my self-worth to be tied to a simple tool. No tool is worth
it. Every tool fails. I&rsquo;d sold myself short, lowered my self-worth to that of a
tool. This completely blocked my ability to be an effective technical leader.</p>

<p>I couldn&rsquo;t hear criticism of my ideas without getting defensive, so I couldn&rsquo;t
think critically. I couldn&rsquo;t help work out solutions to the best of my ability,
because that would mean admitting personal failure. Every side comment or
momentary struggle felt like a catastrophe.</p>

<p>After realizing this, I felt a wave of relief. My emotional struggle leading
this programming language change made sense! And I had an easy way out! I simply
had to distance myself from my ideas, separate my self-worth from my tools. The
more I meditated, the easier it got.</p>

<h2>Present Day</h2>

<p>While I still sometimes get the old pang of embarrassment or defensiveness, now
I understand where it comes from, and how to move forward. I can let my ideas
go. I can consider ideas critically. I can make changes and adjustments if the
ideas are not working.</p>

<p>This summer I decided to write up my learning. I wanted to always be able to
look back and remember these important lessons. My write-up was the seed for the
book <a href="https://leanpub.com/convincingcoworkers">Convincing Coworkers</a>. I explain
the lessons learned from implementing a half dozen major technical changes, and
how I learned to lead without letting my ego cloud my thinking.</p>

<p>If you want to become a more effective leader, I highly recommend a practice of
daily meditation. Meditation gives your mind a chance to deeply consider your
actions and values. It allows your subconscious to reflect on what and why you
act.</p>

<p>Not everyone will struggle from the same issues as me. Every leader has a
different set of challenges and situations. Meditation lets your mind analyze
your unique weaknesses and strengths, coming up with a tailored perspective.
Meditating allows your mind to creatively look for ways to improve itself. While
rarely comfortable, this process can have incredible benefits.</p>

<h2>Appendix: &ldquo;I&rsquo;m uncomfortable with the connotations of meditation&rdquo;</h2>

<p>You may feel uncomfortable with meditation because of its current strong
associations with religion. Meditation is not inherently religious. I consider
meditation like an exercise routine for the mind. If you are religious, and
exercise your body as a form of religious expression, exercise is a religious
practice. If you are not religious, and you exercise to improve your health and
well-being, exercise is a secular practice. Meditation is just a form of mental
exercise. Simple as that.</p>

<p>Meditation is a tool, and the tool wielder determines its use. Don&rsquo;t let a fear
of the connotations of meditation stop you from experiencing improved
leadership, creativity, and focus!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Interview Humiliation]]></title>
    <link href="http://deliberate-software.com/on-defeat/"/>
    <updated>2015-10-29T19:01:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://deliberate-software.com/on-defeat</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>(All these great ideas, but no one is listening? Check out my
book: <a href="https://leanpub.com/convincingcoworkers">Convincing Coworkers</a>)</p>

<p>One day, I went into an interview, and I was humiliated.</p>

<h3>The Setup</h3>

<p>I used to think very highly of myself. This was early on in the Test Driven
Development (TDD) craze, and I was one of the best I knew at it. I knew
interfaces, classes, mocking frameworks, and best practices. I&rsquo;d been taught all
the tricks from some very smart people, and my confidence was high. Not only
that, but I&rsquo;d just finished at work the restoration of an abandoned legacy
codebase to a bug-free, fully tested state completely on my own.</p>

<p>I&rsquo;d shipped Java, PHP, Perl, C#, and VB.NET, and I hadn&rsquo;t been programming more
than a couple years. My first job, they&rsquo;d made me a team lead over some very
senior developers within a year of my hire date. I was learning Clojure and
Common Lisp, and had just shipped an Android game I made entirely alone
(including the 2D physics engine).</p>

<p>I thought I was incredible. Yet, due to an overwhelming sense of Imposter
Syndrome, I keenly knew that there were things I didn&rsquo;t know. I&rsquo;m mostly self
taught, so a lot of common CS concepts felt alien. I was waking up before work
and teaching myself algorithms, lisps, and math.</p>

<p>Enter Company A.</p>

<p>I flew through the phone screen &ldquo;this is the best phone screen we&rsquo;ve seen!&rdquo; Of
course it is. &ldquo;Your resume is very impressive.&rdquo; Oh, I know!</p>

<p>I get to the on-site interview.</p>

<h3>The On-Site</h3>

<p>I hadn&rsquo;t been thoughtful enough to ask what to wear, so I wore a suit. I was
asked to present a project I&rsquo;d worked on, and I picked my recently shipped
physics game that was up on Google Play. I walked into the reception area a few
minutes early.</p>

<pre><code>"You are 25 minutes late."
</code></pre>

<p>What?! I explain that I have the email saying 9:30! No matter, &ldquo;hurry, they are
waiting!&rdquo; Maybe I can salvage this. I walk into a conference room with a dozen
people sitting around a table looking bored and pissed.</p>

<pre><code>"Let's see your presentation."
</code></pre>

<p>I start to open up my laptop. Meanwhile, they start to joke around to each other:</p>

<pre><code>"Oh, wow, Linux, what is this, 2003? I'd hoped I'd never have to see the
grub boot screen again! Can't you afford a real machine?"
</code></pre>

<p>I try to joke back while multitasking with my laptop. They only have the Mac
projector cable. No adapter. I&rsquo;d thought ahead, and handed one of the developers
a thumb drive with the presentation and code. The interviewers are joking and
laughing to each other at my choice of clothes.</p>

<pre><code>"A suit, classic, where are you interviewing after this, a sales job?"
</code></pre>

<p>I roll with it, make some joke about &ldquo;styling&rdquo;. I start presenting about the 2D
physics engine I&rsquo;d written as a learning project for my game. One of the most
interesting parts to me was how I&rsquo;d first written it without any unit testing,
following just Clean Code practices. I then re-wrote it using heavy TDD. The
design turned out very different both times, which I thought was interesting to
see how TDD had influenced the design.</p>

<p>About five minutes in, I am cut off:</p>

<pre><code>"This presentation is bullshit. You have no evidence, nothing valuable to
show, just spurious subjective opinions. You've put up a straw man and now
are trying to knock it down assuming we are idiots. I've seen enough."
</code></pre>

<p>At this point, it has been barely 15 minutes since I walked in. I remain calm
and professional, and start to address the raised concerns. I play the
meta-game, wondering if perhaps this is a test to see how I&rsquo;ll react when
questioned and embarrassed. Even if this wasn&rsquo;t a test, I was determined to be
at my most professional and finish with my head held high.</p>

<p>Five developers walk out before I can finish my first sentence. One of the
remaining six interviewers looks embarrassed and asks if I could live code them
a web scraper in any language instead of the presentation. I turn my laptop
around (still no projector) and ask if PHP is acceptable. They are a Python
shop, and PHP is the closest to what they use that I am comfortable using when
this nervous.</p>

<pre><code>"PHP? Gross. I suppose if it is all you know..."
</code></pre>

<p>Unfortunately, I&rsquo;ve got so much adrenaline in me that it takes me a few tries to
log in. I get on a roll after five minutes, and write the scraper. They throw me
a few more requirements, and within a half hour I&rsquo;ve written stories for and
completed them all. At least two of the interviewers seem quite impressed.
Someone looks at their watch, &ldquo;well, that&rsquo;s all the stories we have, I guess
let&rsquo;s break for lunch.&rdquo;</p>

<p>Lunch is a 35 minute walk up a hill in humid 93F weather, and I am wearing a
suit and dress shoes. When we get back from lunch I am hot, tired, and
foot-sore. I distinctly remember my feet blistering inside my sweat-soaked
patent leather shoes. I am called into the conference room again. At this point,
I am genuinely curious if this is some sort of extreme patience/calmness test,
or if I am being filmed for a reality show. No such luck.</p>

<p>At the head of the table is the developer who &ldquo;called me out&rdquo; for my
presentation. Apparently my lunch mates were supposed to only take an hour, we
took almost 90 minutes. He looks at me, rolls his eyes, and asks in the most
sarcastic tone I have ever heard:</p>

<pre><code>"So, got any questions for me?"
</code></pre>

<p>I ask a few normal questions, meanwhile he is constantly checking his watch and
rolling his eyes. He answers briefly and rudely. I thank him for his time, and
ask him if there is more. He laughs.</p>

<pre><code>"Oh, we are done here."
</code></pre>

<p>I am shown to the door.</p>

<p>I sit in the car for a half hour, wondering what just happened. I look over to
the passenger seat piled high with text books I have been studying, books on
language design, compilers, algorithms, physics engines, TDD, and productivity.</p>

<p>I was asked none of it. I threw up from stress out the car door into their
parking lot.</p>

<h3>Aftermath</h3>

<p>I found out later their recruiter had given me and many other candidates the
wrong time. She was fired shortly after.</p>

<p>I never found out if I had done something to make everyone so angry. I now
suspect that they were massively turned off by a host of things. Polyglot
programming, practicing TDD, the suit, the not Mac, the late arrival, and a bad
presentation probably all contributed to an immediate disqualification. I
rationally realize they were terrible and treated me terribly, but the
embarrassment is still there. I suspect my presentation was terrible from the
get go: that they were expecting some rock-star and instead got me.</p>

<p>A number of times I have woken up in a cold sweat having dreamt about that
interview. In the large scheme of things, a bad interview is such a small thing,
but fear is fear. I still to this day wonder what I did wrong. Was I arrogant,
cocky, insufferable? Did my ego cause them to treat me that way, or was it all
them? What could I have done differently? I was only in there for a few minutes!</p>

<p>Few events in my professional life have shaped me as much as that interview. I
have turned it into a forge for my talent, the anvil on which I beat my pride.
When I don&rsquo;t know something, I am more willing to shrug and laugh it off, all
while learning as fast as I can. When I am humiliated professionally, I know
I&rsquo;ve come through worse and thrived.</p>

<h3>Break The Cycle</h3>

<p>This story fills me with an overwhelming desire to never continue the cycle of
abuse. I strive every interview to try to respectfully work with the candidate,
and never humiliate them. I want every person I interview to leave feeling loved
as a human and respected, even if they are completely incapable to perform the
duties of the job.</p>

<p>When I ask a question, if they struggle, we work it out together. When I ask for
code, we write it together, even if that means I have to do all the work. I can
make myself their servant, while still assessing their skill with accuracy and
dispassion. Those with the skill will show it, and those without will not feel
humiliated. I let them interview me, and if that means they want me to go up to
the whiteboard and struggle through a merge sort, so be it. In this way, I push
back against the interview culture that normalizes degradation and humiliation.</p>

<p>If you are interviewing others, take a serious look at your practices. Would a
failed candidate feel humiliated and disrespected? What will they tell their
coworkers and friends at meetups about your company? Will they talk about
feeling respected, and how they hope to get the chance to work with you one day?
Or will they talk of a group of self-righteous jerks who abuse their power to
make others feel small? You can break the cycle.</p>

<p>(All these great ideas, but no one is listening? Check out my
book: <a href="https://leanpub.com/convincingcoworkers">Convincing Coworkers</a>)</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Software Skills Continuum]]></title>
    <link href="http://deliberate-software.com/skill-continuum/"/>
    <updated>2014-12-02T07:26:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://deliberate-software.com/skill-continuum</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<pre><code>    Learning Vim is a waste of time; I can prove it! - Anonymous
</code></pre>

<p>I recently had a gentle discussion with a new teammate about whether
or not they should learn to use Vim. My team uses a Vim emulator
inside Visual Studio and Emacs, and so we recommended he learn at
least the basics so to reduce friction when pair-programming (which we
do almost all the time).</p>

<p>He really had no desire to learn it, and took no small amount of
offense when we suggested it. The friction he felt trying to &ldquo;start
over&rdquo; really bothered him. He set out to prove that Vim was not worth
his time, and that it was actually us who needed to stop using it,
because we were the duped slow ones.</p>

<p>As any such localized experiments go, he never really came up with
anything conclusive either way. Personally, I suspect he spent more
time trying to figure out why Vim was worse than if he had just
buckled down and learned it. This got me thinking about skills we
learn as developers, and how much they cost.</p>

<h1>Skills</h1>

<p>Most skills fall along a continuum of tactical to strategic.</p>

<h3>Tactical Skills</h3>

<ul>
<li>Typing speed/accuracy</li>
<li>Keyboard shortcuts</li>
<li>&ldquo;Mouse-free&rdquo; editing systems: Vim, Emacs</li>
<li>Clean coding practices</li>
<li>Refactoring tools</li>
<li>Repl Driven Development / Test Driven Development</li>
<li>Debugging</li>
</ul>


<h3>Mid-way Skills</h3>

<ul>
<li>Unit testing</li>
<li>Building abstractions</li>
<li>Designing simple solutions</li>
<li>Automating tasks</li>
<li>Learning new languages and frameworks</li>
</ul>


<h3>Strategic Skills</h3>

<ul>
<li>Gathering requirements</li>
<li>Training developers</li>
<li>Organizing and leading teams</li>
<li>&ldquo;Understanding the real problem&rdquo;</li>
</ul>


<p>The more strategic the skills, the &ldquo;softer&rdquo; they become. The reason for this is
that soft skills often allow for the greatest leverage on a project.</p>

<p>Why is this?</p>

<p>Consider the developer, who by more accurately gathering requirements for a few
extra days, realizes that the stakeholder can use a preexisting solution instead
of a six month planned project. If you consider how many keystrokes he saved,
there is no way he could have typed fast enough to make up six months of effort.
Unless he can type out a six month project in a few days, his time was better
spent where it was. Obviously, these opportunities do not happen all the time,
but they <em>do</em> happen and it doesn&rsquo;t take more than one or two a year to have
major impact!</p>

<p>Think about the return on investment for training developers. If you have an
average team (and yes, we all do), there is a good chance you have some lower
performing developers. I have witnessed many times where a few months of pairing
to brush up the skills of a less skilled developer allowed them to become much
more productive. In terms of total company effort, that small investment paid
back many times before the end of the year as the newly trained developer was
able to tackle their work with the renewed vigor that comes from a greater
mastery of their work.</p>

<p>Similarly, the judicious use of automation for deployment, testing, and building
greatly reduces the friction of development for entire teams. Lowered friction
means less cognitive burden.</p>

<p>That being said, I think there comes a point where you have to put fingers to
keyboard and actually produce working software. Of course, the fastest and best
software is the software you never have to write. But, when you absolutely must
write or modify software, the ability to execute is essential. Tactical skills
increase in significance the closer you get to the work.</p>

<p>While a great software tactician will never &ldquo;beat&rdquo; a great strategist in terms
of raw business value, a great strategist that is a terrible tactician can only
talk their way out of work. A strategist who forgets or ignores good tactics is
what we call an &ldquo;architecture astronaut&rdquo; or an &ldquo;ivory tower architect&rdquo;. These
disconnected strategists eventually start to remove business value as their
solutions make less and less practical sense.</p>

<p>I think a developer who wants to improve should make sure they are improving all
across the spectrum. Don&rsquo;t focus only on strategic or tactical skills, but seek
projects and teams that will allow you to gain skills across the board. I like
to try to focus on one skill from each side of the continuum each year. This
year, it is emacs automation and monads on the tactical side, and leading mature
teams on the strategic. By alternating readings, I find fuel to apply the
strategies using these new tactics!</p>

<p>Lastly, on the subject of &ldquo;what to study&rdquo;, I think it is possible to study a
number of subjects all across the continuum. Unless you have weeks where you
never type any code at all, you can practice and learn new tactical techniques
all the time. If it slows you down today, but speeds you up next week, it might
just be worth it. Even if it slowed you down to a quarter your usual speed for
two weeks, but then gives you a measly 5% boost to productively after that,
you&rsquo;ll earn that time back by the end of the year, plus some. And 5% is not hard
to do. I&rsquo;d guess learning a few new navigation or refactoring shortcuts would
net you 5% easily.</p>

<p>When studying more strategic skills, the same holds, but they are harder to
learn. The best way I have found for learning strategic skills is to read books
about it, and try to work around others who are good at it. Neither books or
working with others will get you all the way there, you also have to apply it
yourself.</p>

<h1>Progression</h1>

<p>I usually recommend that the more experienced a person is, the more mastery they
should have in the tactical skills. A suggested path I&rsquo;ve recommended for a new
developer would look like this:</p>

<h3>0 - 6 Months:</h3>

<ul>
<li>Typing speed/accuracy</li>
<li>Keyboard shortcuts</li>
<li>Repl Driven Development / Test Driven Development</li>
<li>Unit testing</li>
<li>Clean coding practices</li>
<li>Designing simple solutions</li>
</ul>


<h3>0 - 2 Years:</h3>

<ul>
<li>Debugging</li>
<li>Refactoring tools</li>
<li>Building abstractions</li>
<li>Automating tasks</li>
<li>Learning new languages and frameworks</li>
<li>&ldquo;Mouse-free&rdquo; editing systems: Vim, Emacs</li>
</ul>


<h3>0 - 50+ Years:</h3>

<ul>
<li>Gathering requirements</li>
<li>Training developers</li>
<li>Organizing and leading teams</li>
<li>Understanding the real problem</li>
</ul>


<p>This is not a hard and fast list. If you are completely unsure of what to learn,
I recommend this rough progression just to get you started. If you are a two
year developer, and you cannot touch type, I think learning it can really help,
alongside the other 0 - 2 year skills.</p>

<p>Not all skills along the list build on a mastery of the ones below it. A
developer can absolutely get to a very senior mastery of the strategic skills
only knowing one language and using notepad.exe. I believe that they are missing
out on a deep richness that comes from better knowing their field, and I suggest
they spend some time learning new languages and tools. The more tactical the
skill, usually, the easier it is to learn, so it won&rsquo;t take very much time to
come up to speed.</p>

<p>The hardest thing I think a more senior developer has to deal with is humbling
themselves to learn a perceived &ldquo;entry-level&rdquo; skill. I have another post brewing
about this very topic, so I&rsquo;ll not get too much into it here. But if you have
gotten to a place where you feel like you are so senior that some skills are too
&ldquo;entry-level&rdquo; for you to learn, I think you need to humble yourself and learn
them. Nothing can be gained from pretending like they are not valuable.
Additionally, the assumption that your time is now so valuable that it is &ldquo;a
waste&rdquo; to spend it on learning tactical skills is absurd.</p>

<p>Claiming you are too good to waste on low level skills not only belittles
everyone around you, but belies a deep misunderstanding of our field. The senior
developer who takes five times as long to enter and edit code isn&rsquo;t just
spending longer to do that task, but they are paying a missed opportunity cost
in time they could have spent in more strategic endeavors. They could have been
training, planning, gathering requirements, building better automation, etc,
instead they stubbornly claim &ldquo;typing isn&rsquo;t what software is about&rdquo;. By giving
it so little credence, they have made it most of their actual mental effort!
Take simple touch-typing. Imagine how much mental effort it takes the
hunt-and-peck typist to write out a single line of code. That is mental overhead
that is simply wasted. The developer who doesn&rsquo;t have to think about how to move
a file or edit a structure finds themselves quickly through the tactical efforts
with little distraction, free to think deeply.</p>

<h1>Resources</h1>

<p>Here are some links and books to get you started on these topics.</p>

<ul>
<li>Typing speed/accuracy - <a href="http://store.steampowered.com/agecheck/app/246580/">Typing of the Dead</a></li>
<li>&ldquo;Mouse-free&rdquo; editing systems: Vim, Emacs - <a href="http://vim-adventures.com/">Vim Adventures</a></li>
<li>Clean coding practices - <a href="https://cleancoders.com/">Clean Coders</a></li>
<li>Repl Driven Development - <a href="http://blog.jayfields.com/2014/01/repl-driven-development.html">RDD</a></li>
<li>Test Driven Development - <a href="http://www.amazon.com/Test-Driven-Development-By-Example/dp/0321146530">http://www.amazon.com/Test-Driven-Development-By-Example/dp/0321146530</a></li>
<li>Debugging - <a href="http://c.learncodethehardway.org/book/ex31.html">Debugging</a></li>
<li>Building abstractions / Designing Simple Solutions - <a href="http://mitpress.mit.edu/sicp/full-text/book/book-Z-H-4.html#%_toc_start">Structure and Interpretation of Computer Programs</a></li>
<li>Training developers - <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pair_programming">Pair Programming</a></li>
<li>Organizing and leading teams - <a href="http://managinghumans.com/">Managing Humans</a></li>
<li>Understanding the real problem - <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Thinking,_Fast_and_Slow">Thinking Fast and Slow</a></li>
<li>Learning new languages and frameworks - <a href="http://norvig.com/21-days.html">Teach Yourself Programming in Ten Years</a></li>
<li>Automating tasks <a href="http://www.stuartellis.eu/articles/rake/">Rake to Automate Tasks</a></li>
</ul>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
